[Music]
[Applause]
okay let's go and so I have a very
ambitious plan today I would like to
teach you the whole structure of wisdom
okay
I'd like to teach you and Tony nominee
in his commentary and it's very
beautiful it's brilliant but it's too
long to put on your home run okay it's
like 54 things or something you know
there cuz it's a chapter name and then
there's a chapter meaning okay and side
I was thinking how to get it on your
homework
I had a inspiration I translated those
three to three pages where Tony Lama
explains the whole structure of the
whole book and it's gonna we're gonna be
doing this for five years and the
structure is very important so you guys
are the lucky ones you're going to hear
it from the beginning and I won't do
this structure again so I think it's
very important so I had a nice idea
maybe you don't think so but I put the
whole translation on your homework okay
the whole translation is on your
homework but there are blank spots
understand so you just fill them in from
your notes okay so for this homework
you're allowed to use your notes and
listen carefully this first question
which is three pages long it's not on
your quiz so fun song just relax
what do you go in espanol okay just
relax it's not on your quiz okay bye
basically get the name of the chapter
and get the meaning of the chapter so 27
times to write 54 now the other cute
thing is and and then on your homework
you just fill in the blank space okay
easy but and I can't explain the whole
book in one hour but I can give it a
structure and it's very beautiful
okay now Tony Lama does a very cool
thing he creates a flow of the whole
book okay so like he starts with chapter
8 and then he'll be jumping around and
and he saw a flow to see the whole book
and his commentary is unbelievable
unbelievable it's like after 2,000 years
somebody wrote 13 how many years since
it's Indian 1600 years he he saw this
flow and I believe it's correct okay so
here we go
basically you're gonna write three
things chapter number next to that
chapter name next to that what's it
about oftentimes the name tells you
oftentimes the name doesn't tell you
okay here we go so fasten your seat belt
if you fall asleep I'm gonna hit you in
something okay all right so the most
dangerous kind of misunderstanding right
misunderstanding like in the kitchen if
you misunderstand the husband you will
yell back okay the most dangerous kind
of misunderstanding is focused at me
Michael and so Michaels misunderstanding
most dangerous one is focused on Michael
and it sees things about Michael that
are not there like the second husband in
the kitchen okay so misunderstanding me
and misunderstanding mine might me and
mine okay Michael and Michael's Buddha
and Buddha's power and bowels okay
misunderstanding those things okay it's
the subject of chapter 18
I said chapter and I I made a mistake
it starts with chapter 18 18 and it's
about the me and the mine that don't
exist the me and the mine that don't
exist okay for example in your
meditation you fight to meditate and
thoughts come up and you say no we're
meditating don't think about that guy
okay yeah you said something yesterday
forget it and you fight with your mind
okay but sometimes your mind listen and
sometimes your mind doesn't listen
because actually you cannot control your
mind your mind is like the husband in
the kitchen okay if you were nice to
other people last week the mind will be
quiet during meditation if you are not
nice to people last week I don't care
what kind of meditation cushion you buy
I don't care how you put your feet left
foot first right foot first you hold
this finger you hold this finger it
doesn't matter it won't work because
because your meditation is seeds coming
out of your mind okay it's not you it's
just seeds coming out of your mind okay
that's me and in my meditation okay so
that's the subject of chapter 18 the
name of chapter 18 is what's the first
word
an examination pariksha an examination
of the person and things the person and
things okay every chapter is an
examination 27 different proofs of
emptiness minimum okay
27 different proofs of emptiness let's
take Peter murders left ear let's do an
examination of Peter murders left ear
okay like that could also be a chapter
28 okay so each time we're gonna pick
something okay I don't know but it's
gonna be an examination okay how does it
exist how can it work and the answer is
it cannot okay here we go second part
then the next chapter he lists is
chapter 2 and chapter 8 he puts them
together chapter 2 and chapter 8 and he
says if you prove there's no person to
somebody then they're gonna think two
things well and we had these in kamila
Sheena we had these in combination well
if there's no person who makes karma you
know in 2018 and gets it back in 2019
who's there
if there's no person well who does the
Karma and who gets it back worth the
connection if there's no person okay so
chapter 2 and chapter 8 our reaction to
chapter 18 okay and they ask another
question
well guess law if there's no dentist
if dentist doesn't exist then who goes
to the next life
okay who goes to the next lab who is it
that goes to the next life okay those
are two questions that come up if
there's no person which we learned in
chapter 18 then two questions come up
well whose connection between doing the
Karma and getting back to Karma
and who's the person connection between
this life and next life if there's no
person then who is it what is it okay
chapter eight okay
I think is the answer to the good and
bad karma question okay and it's called
what's the first word
an examination of doers and what they do
doers and what they do people who do
things and the things they do do door
and what they do okay karma and result
of karma right
chapter two and I think it must connect
to past like next life and this line is
called what's the first word an
examination of coming and going actually
it's going and coming okay an
examination of going and coming okay
is it possible to go is it possible to
come is it possible to do anything okay
the answer is no one kind of doing
things all right so it's taking off a
little bit from Chapter eight one kind
of doing things is perception you see
colors you see shapes you hear sounds
you taste coffee okay that's one kind of
doing things okay and that's chapter 9
okay
and this is a really cool question
okay ready are you underwater not yet
chapter 9 and examination of whether
things are there before you proceed them
very cool question an examination
chapter 9 of whether things are there or
not before you see them
okay did you come in the room and count
was here already or did you come in the
room and create care which one okay
that's a cool chapter I'm looking
forward to these chapters okay all right
now somebody else said when I come in
the room and I see cat cat really exists
and my mind really exists and and they
affect each other she was here before I
came in I walked in I looked over there
she's there they're happy to have you
guys here today thank you for coming and
then there's some kind of interaction
between lama palma and cat and in my
eyes there's there's some kind of
touching going on right and the other
guy says okay the other guy says it's
like a match and wood it's like a match
and some firewood okay the match cause
the fire okay the match you like the
match you touch the wood it has to touch
and then there'll be a fire okay he
tries to tell the gardener look cat is
like the wood your mind is like the
match then the match touches the cat and
then you have cat you see cat they the
mind that I touches can okay it's just
like Matt and and wood okay he uses an
example which is wrong okay but we
should examine it who said that that's
nice that's cool we should examine this
guy's idea does the match have to touch
the wood okay so the chapter is called
an examination of fire and fire wood
chapter 10 chapter 10
an examination of fire and fire wood and
that's not our example it's his example
and it's wrong somehow somehow that
example gets us into the question of
whether there is a beginning or an
ending to things and this is one of the
famous questions asked to the Buddha
which he refused to answer you know was
there a beginning which came first the
chicken or the egg you know and which
will be last a chicken or an egg and
Buddha fight don't ask any answer I give
you you're gonna miss understand so I
refused to answer 14 unanswered
questioning
okay so chapter 11 it I'm guessing I
don't know for sure cuz I'm also
learning this book as we go I'm guessing
that if cat was here before I got here
then is there any beginning to things
and if there any end to things okay
that's so that's the question
chapter 11 examine is there a beginning
and is there an ending okay and he
connected to catch chapter 12 because
these questions about life are really
about pain what causes our pain what
makes us mortal you know why do we lose
our hair in the middle but we get extra
in the ears I don't know
okay what caused this suffering this is
chapter 12 also coming from the chapter
10 rent and examination of whether pain
was created by ourselves or was it
created by something else okay was it
created by my husband in the kitchen or
was it created by me who created my
problems okay in life we all have
problems we all spend time in retreat
thinking about our problems
it seems like when you get quiet you
have more time to think about your
promise so did I do this to myself or
are other people hurting me which one
okay that's chapter 12 okay cool
[Applause]
then it goes to the first chapter okay
like where did these problems come from
this is the first chapter which is
called an examination of I'm going to
change the translation to conditions I
said factors before but he uses factors
again later
so conditions causes and conditions okay
from the gardener and for the Buddha in
this case conditions means causes you
can think causes the name is conditions
it just means causes usually conditions
means fertilizer sunlight water and
cause means in trees feed okay but here
it's a general word for all causes okay
so if things are not themselves how do
they start okay we have to examine kind
of things start from some power of its
own kind of things start some power of
its own
Kenneth does a seed for a tree cat
planted a nice thick chain over there is
it still there I haven't been there for
awhile halfway there did you plant a
seed an actual seat like a pit person
thing yeah so you can go see her peach
tree it's still there
trees don't laughing desert very well
then there must be some power in the pit
that I can create a peach tree okay so
do things do causes conditions have some
power inside of them okay that's chapter
one by the way that's the chapter we're
going to spend most of this week on okay
and it's very deep you will be dizzy by
the time we finish you'll run home to
get away from the gardener okay so
basically it teaches that the power to
grow a tree is not inside a seed and the
power to upset you doesn't exist in your
husband it's all coming from you there's
no power in the husband there's no power
in this thing if the seed makes a peach
tree the seed and the tree are coming
from you okay and the seed has no power
then someone says wait a minute you mean
seeds are not themselves right all the
other stuff that Buddha talked about
especially in the early part of his life
okay so today they're not themselves
why did Buddha talk about them if they
don't have any quality if they don't
have any name
if they don't do what they do by
themselves if it's all coming from me
why did Buddha make a big list of all
the things in the world well what what
was the whole first part of his teaching
about abhidharma okay
so there's three chapters there okay
number five an examination of the
categories categories category means
good I divided the world into 18
categories Buddha divided the world into
18 categories six objects right which
are visible things sounds smells tastes
touches and thoughts okay six objects
okay then there are six powers sense
powers that see them the eye the ear the
nose the tongue the skin and the mind
okay mental sense and then there's six
awareness of what you're seeing what
you're hearing what you're smelling what
you're tasting what you're feeling and
what you're thinking 18 total six
objects six objects six powers and six
awareness since eighteen okay so that's
Chapter five
do these have any power of their own
okay
chapter five chapter three examination
of the powers of sense your eyes your
ears your nose your tongue your body
your mind okay
Chapter six sorry chapter three you know
and chapter four an examination of the
heaps heaps means body and mind okay in
the West we say body in mind in Buddhism
we say the the three mental three and a
half mental parts and yeah I mean like
that you can call it the five parts to a
five part impressive very famous in
Buddhism subway Kong Kong boys answer
dyskinesia sure something she evolution
like that five heaps okay five parts of
person okay alright
by the way some smart person I think
it's been call me it's gonna keep track
did we cover all the chapters or not
okay like it took me about an hour and
two to check that he doesn't mention 27
chapters or not okay
we're trying to get to 27 but it's all
over right okay alright then somebody
comes along and says look things start
things stay for a while and then things
stop okay and the cause of that is
somebody doing something like we started
the road project then all the Singapore
and Malaysia and Indonesia people and
the Chinese people don't and some
Canadian and American donate and German
donate money and then we finished the
world okay so something caused the thing
to start keeping keep the project going
which is Michael Dunn and then somebody
finished the project okay three things
start going and finishing okay somebody
starts it ok karma and people okay and
we get emotions and he mentions desire
okay he starts with desire and those
also have causes something starts them
so don't those have some nature of their
own okay it's not like I can feel happy
and then I'm jealous
happy cannot cost job
next moment okay so they must have some
nature those thoughts in my mind must
have some nature okay they must be
coming from their side okay turn it
things that start and stay and go and
emotions like attachment and desire they
must have some nature okay to respond to
that we have three chapters okay chapter
six
an examination of desire and attachment
okay do they have some nature of their
own or are they coming from something
else okay Chapter seven
an examination of how things start and
stay and stop an examination of how
things start and stay and stop okay
Chapter seven yeah Chapter seven then he
throws in chapter 13 okay
an examination of factors and he uses
another name for conditions so I didn't
know about chapter 13 I was working on
chapter one so I called it the chapter
an examination of factors but then later
he used a better word for factors so now
I have to change this chapter to an
examination of conditions okay
chapter one an examination of conditions
chapter thirteen and examination of
factors and they're pretty much the same
in Buddhism let's find out what happens
okay
[Music]
then some people come along and say
people and things must have something
inside of them geshe-la
come on the glass has something inside
of it that makes it hard the glass has
something inside of it that makes it
hard there's something inside a glass
that makes it hard okay then the guard
says why is why you think done why I
think there has to be something inside
okay and they said well there's three
examples we can give okay and these are
going to be different chapters okay so
this is a reaction the Guardian is
answering three wrong ideas okay number
one how can things touch each other okay
how can things touch each other
geshe-la pushes the clock towards the
edge of the table there must be some
contact between gas laws hand and the
clock must be it's moving
is there no you have seized for arm to
move and you have seats for clock to
move and the moving of the arm doesn't
cause the clock to move
really okay really you have to think
like that
why then you can make stuff happen then
you can have anything you want
thank you you see if you understand that
you don't keep trying to push your
friends you see you just change them
here okay
much easier all right stop trying to do
something to make something happen you
know I have this person hurt me I don't
like them go to get I'll getcha maybe
guess I will push the person you know
come on what school are you but your
mind is better to take care of it than
guess you know there's a lot of fail
sometimes your mind always succeed all
right all right so anyway do things make
contact that is answered in chapter 14
that is answered in chapter 14 an
examination of where other things ever
touch each other an examination of
whether things ever touch okay then
people say well learn you gotta have
causes and condition to make things
happen
okay the road didn't just pop there we
did fundraising blood sweat and tears
undressing now I walk on that road I
want to kiss the road it's a little icky
but I think I might do it anyway you
know I'm so happy with this road we
should
Michael Dunn's not here well thank him
oh he is Michael Dunn let's give him a
hand
in 2003 we took 20 people up there and
we cleared rocks to make about 10 meters
of road it took us a week and anyway
Michael Dunn did it in a few weeks okay
so they say look geshe-la you have to
have money to make the road there must
be sponsored there must be workers there
must be machines there must be cause of
the road right those so we go to chapter
an examination of I'll give you a choice
okay you tell me which is correct ready
an examination of a nature two things or
an examination of the nature two things
a why in English a means maybe it exists
maybe it doesn't exist a supposed nature
thing and when you say da it means I
believe it okay English is very
sensitive okay that's how I check a
translation if they say third nature I
throw the book out it's so cool
darn it you know because there is no
nature you see I mean it's a it's a
supposed to meet you I think okay
all right that's chapter 15 is there in
nature in things okay
can they do what they do from their own
son okay then we applied that question
to rebirth cycle of rebirths okay is
there something you do in this life
which has a nature of creating next time
okay and that chapters chapter 16
and it's called an examination of
bondage and liberation bondage means
they are like in the jail okay
bondage in English means you are like in
the jail and then liberation can you get
out okay so that's chapter one six
sixteen sixteen and it's talking about
what causes Ripper okay is there a
nature to something where it causes
remember the answer is no in this class
just say no you're safe in DC I what do
you have to do what's the answer to
everything
what's there okay in the gardening class
no don't exist I like the next chapter I
think it's very sexy
chapter 17 okay now that we're on the
subject of samsara cycle of pain where's
this ansara in the kitchen you you yell
at the husband that put some seed here
and then next week the kids don't change
from their pajamas okay and you yell at
them and then next week husband yell at
you and and that's a censor asons are
there are many sensors okay everything
in our life is in samsara okay all right
they say there must be some connection
between karma and its results there has
to be a connection between karma and its
results there has to be a nature there
there has to be something there
okay guys know if it's coming from me
then I will get pizza from everything
and I won't gain any weight when I eat
the pizza you see like we've made
connection between karma and
consequences who made the connection you
know you lie to people then people lie
to you who made the connection okay yeah
where's it come from that must be
natural it must be in the universe it's
not me I'm not God God I I didn't make
this I didn't make a rule if you do a
good thing you get a good result if you
do bad thing you get back that come on
get LA I was born in universe the
universe already had this law right good
now you learn how to enter ok so chapter
17 I think it's extremely important it
sounds really sexy I can't wait to get
to chapter 17 an examination of karma
and its consequences
an examination of karma and its results
ok chapter 17
chapter 19 very very cool
I don't know which is more cool
photography time cool Oh
an examination of time time okay
geshe-la
look past has a nature it's gone present
has a nature it's here
future has a nature is yet to come you
can't change those those have real
nature those have real time it's real
you know time doesn't get shorter time
doesn't get longer time has its own time
I didn't make it you know I didn't make
them an hour 60 minutes okay I think
that's very important for supposedly
after you see emptiness directly you
have an experience that lasts about 20
minutes where you see the face of every
living being in the universe and love
them at the same time so time has to
shrink like a billion years has to
become 20 minutes you see and it's that
possible if time has its own nature or
if its time coming from me you see so
that guy when you got to chapter 19 the
other guy
all these examinations are because some
other guy comes up and says look the
guy's not ok karma doesn't have its own
nature but there's no connection karma
and its result I got it but time you
know answer me that one doesn't a time
having so Nature doesn't a minute takes
60 seconds no gardener you know isn't it
always like that
and the gardener says no
but I would be interesting to see the
proof yeah looking 27 proofs I hope okay
then somebody said if time doesn't come
from itself if time doesn't come from
itself then what about the time it takes
the cause to make the result okay if
there's no time
if time is flexible if time is coming
from me then what about the time it
takes from the nursing home to the
boyfriend okay what about the time it
boyfriend geshe-la you always say six
weeks eight weeks
- love's always exaggerating sometimes
it takes a hundred years okay don't tell
anybody
don't tell the DCI people you know what
about the time it takes things to to
come and take time to disappear you know
if I make the right seats my husband
will not refuse to wash the dishes okay
yeah but how long does it take okay so
we have two chapters about done number
20 an examination of how our causes and
conditions come together like water
fertilizer sunlight and and see seed is
the cause those other things are
conditions how do they come together
what makes them come together okay
something in them right no good to say
no
do you want to break no you have to
pee-pee no chapter 21 and exempt an
examination how about how things appear
and disappear
an examination of how things appear and
disappear chapter 21 things you know
relatives die new sources of irritation
arise in your life
so now someone says look in the guide
you know all that you're basically
proving there's no Sun Sara there's no
circle of pain no wheel of life you are
you are proving there's no wheel of life
okay that's you seem to be thinking like
this all the stuff you said you know
you're saying there's no dependence
there's no wheel of life you know
which means there's no negative emotions
anger hatred jealousy desire okay then
then they can't exist the cause of the
wheel are they they don't exist
and how about the people who got out of
the wheel Buddhist in the Wheel of Life
the Buddha like doing what pointing to
the moon okay if there's no wheel of
mine
well what about Buddhists who got out
and inside the wheel of life what about
these negative emotions that are pushing
it pushing the wheel of life you know
according to you there's no real
reliable there's no Carmen there's no
consequences nothing cause anything else
then how can you have a real life how
can you be in the wheel of life and how
can you be out of the real life so we
have chapter 22 is an examination of
Buddhas this cool how can there be a
Buddha okay chapter 22 how can there be
Buddha's okay chapter 23 and
examinations of all the mistakes you can
make in your life that keep you in the
wheel okay it's called an examination of
mistakes biggest mistake yeah you think
the husband decided to yell are you okay
you think the husband is coming this way
okay biggest number one mistake okay
then somebody comes up ok ok no God you
know I got it
there's nothing real in the whole world
nothing is real nothing is true nothing
has any nature of its own right didn't
that the Guardian know well I mean
that's in the garden instead nothing is
real nothing exists
nothing is true and then the guy says
huh Four Noble Truths four are your two
scoops ok for higher truth what about
does so they don't exist
ok why you say that huh
use that nothing's true use that
nothing's real ok there's no four truths
right
there's no no first teaching of the
Buddha huh the gardener okay so guess
what chapter 24 is called an examination
of the four truths the fortress okay if
nothing's true if nothing's real you
know he should have taken a vacation
after he got in mind why teach the four
truth okay they don't exist according to
you they don't exist okay and if there's
a world like that where there's nothing
real and nothing true and no teaching on
the truth then there's no nirvana then
there's no Nirvana so we better have a
chapter called an examination of Nirvana
chapter 25 okay
an examination of Nirvana he's covering
a lot of stuff okay
then the next one okay we're almost done
right Ben comas gonna tell you we have
two chapters to go I think okay now here
listen okay the Buddha said that if you
understand that the husband is coming
from you if you understand then you have
seen the middle way then you understand
the middle way okay if you understand
that the husband is coming from you in
the kitchen when he's yelling then you
understand the middle way you are middle
way okay
so therefore according to Tony lama
chapter 26 is called an examination of
the twelve links of the cycle of pain an
examination of the twelve links of the
cycle of pain The Wheel of Life
an examination of The Wheel of Life okay
Choni Lama believes that's a
presentation of the middle way middle
very cool very cool usually we say the
teaching on the Wheel of Life is lower
Hinayana lower school right the gardener
says arm you understand that wheel you
understand the middle way okay you
understand that wheel you understand the
middle way he's equates understanding
the wheel to finding the middle way okay
cool so chapter 26 is called an
examination of the twelve links okay of
the wheel of life
and if you understand that we are okay
listen all right why did Nagarjuna bow
down to the Buddha in the first verse
yeah because the Buddha taught
dependence but it wasn't ordinary
dependence it was emptiness jalapeno
dependence okay it was heavy spice it
had the spice of emptiness okay so
there's two ways to teach the way of
life
okay one is lower way ba-ba-ba-ba-ba
wanted higher way this wheel is also
empty okay everything in the wheel all
twelve links is also empty everything's
empty about the wheel the gardener
bounced down to the Buddha because he
taught both past life in the lions dance
and the emptiness of that teachers good
quality okay the lions dance also has
bone okay dependence you go to your path
line emptiness you see your teachers
good quality is not coming from them
okay that's a sweet dependence that's
what you call your own super dependent
okay yo Chou panchak why I know donut in
every language not sure okay alright so
chapter 27 last chapter is called an
examination of viewpoints viewpoints how
do you view the world do you think the
husband comes from the husband or you
think the husband comes from you okay
this is what is your viewpoint so if you
see that the wheel is empty you have
correct viewpoint
you have a correct view point so 27 is
examination of view points you just got
a summary of the entire wisdom which is
super cool that don't forget your only
job is to fill in the missing names
sometimes I pick an easy one sometimes I
don't pick an easy one okay all right
now I believe that due to your
excitement about this subject you have
proved that you deserve a pee-pee break
okay so call 15-minute break is that the
right time or did I do too soon it's
good
tim has to go so okay take a break 15
minutes you did a good job or you made
it too
okay let's continue each of the
examinations is more or less a reaction
to somebody's wrong ideas so when we say
examination it's kind of assumed that we
are examining somebody else's wrong idea
about like there must be a connection
between karma and results from its own
side there must be connection okay so
then we have to do an examination of
this question what's the connection you
see and then so everything we every
chapter is a response to somebody else's
question and the guards you know
debating with the Guardian is hopeless
right
super hopeless and so every chapter and
some of them are very short some of them
are half a page but they are very very
compact and they are very powerful and
very what he call like a like a gun you
know
- this guy's thoughts so Tony Lama said
he pauses here and he says I want to
make one thing clear the purpose of
these examinations and the debate is not
to argue with other people okay so he
said don't think like that okay the
purpose of the examination is not to
hurt the other school or the other
people it's to improve ourselves okay
it's to improve ourselves all right
so each examination the reason for it
the debating this other person is to
improve ourselves and then he says three
levels of improvement this might be on
your homework along with what he's not
doing right number one if you study
these examinations you plant a seed in
yourself to reach liberation okay if you
studied these 27 examinations you plant
a seed inside yourself to reach
liberation number two because the
examinations are based on difficult
questions your practice will become more
and more strong because those doubts
won't come up in your mind anymore okay
twenty-seven doubts won't come up in
your mind you kind of shoot them down
before they take off and so your own
practice will be stronger and less
less open to doubts that might hurt your
practice okay third thing the practice
itself will become stronger and stronger
you become inspired to work harder and
harder okay if you study these 27 okay
and it's not just I think a lot of
people
I heard someone told me you guys are in
your head you're not in your heart you
know and I'm I thought about it because
usually I'd like to debate you know and
I'm like and I felt like I should debate
this then I said you know you're right
we get to the heart through the head
you know we get to vote each other
through on this we think it's very
important to understand the husband in
the kitchen then you can love the
husband you see I mean but if you don't
understand that is coming from you you
you can't love him anyway it'll never
[Music]
stay strong the love will break okay
when things can hide the level bring you
see some so it sounds very intellectual
this class sounds kind of philosophical
but you're supposed to use it in the
kitchen okay you're supposed to take
this class to the kitchen why we always
mentioning husband or wife because 90%
of husbands and wives need this class
okay because it's difficult to be
married to someone it's difficult to
have a relationship okay and if you
understand where they're coming from it
gets easier okay
all right nice Hummer question the
second verse of wisdom which I'm gonna
go get for you let me see
okay nose
NOS watanabe pirata not vivillon nappy
object or aponogeton Vedanta Baba
Janaki channa things don't come from
themselves things don't come from
something else things don't come from
both and things don't come without a
cost okay I'll say it again slower
results don't come from themselves
results don't come from something else
results don't come from both and results
don't come from nothing Lupo condom
condom kill enemy ano Mayan nothing ever
starts nothing ever starts nothing in
the universe ever starts because there's
nothing to start from a tree can't grow
from the seed a tree can't grow from the
tree the tree can't grow from both and
the tree can't go from nothing okay same
thing so the garden is starting off on
emptiness this is really the first
working verse and it says look all the
things that come from other things they
don't okay all the things that come from
other things they don't okay
was the husband just hungry and that's
why he yelled in the kitchen was the
husband hungry not hungry both or
neither we're trying to discuss why the
husband's in a bad mood you see why is
the husband in bad mood why is your
husband in bad mood tonight
well you know I got home late he didn't
have dinner okay so did the bad mood
come from not enough dinner too much
dinner both or no dinner like which one
came from give me give me choose one of
these four you know this is like diamond
deal right this is like you should buy
this car it's old but it's cheap or you
can buy this car it's new but it's
expensive you choose and then you say
give me a good car that's cheap and I'll
take it
okay give me the right car don't offer
me these two bad choices okay got it for
bad choices all right and that's the
very very famous first kind of working
verse and and we are examining what's
the name of the first chapter
examination of conditions right and
we're gonna look at causes basically
we're gonna look at causes from the
point of view of the result and from the
point of view of the cause
okay we're gonna look at causes from the
point of view of what comes from the
cause and then what the cause makes okay
so right now we're looking at results
okay
actually we're looking at the results of
conditions okay
your husband is upset when you walk in
the kitchen your husband is upset I'll
give you a choice okay he's upset
because he didn't have enough dinner
he's upset because he had too much
dinner he's upset because he had both
and he's upset not because of yes yeah
because there's no dinner you see I mean
I'll give you four choices why he's
upset which one
good yeah no nothing we are in wisdom
nothing so Sunday Godzilla gives you
these four choices these are very very
very famous okay and if you study any
kind of Buddhism China Tibet Korea Japan
doesn't matter you will see these proofs
and now you know where they come from
now you know who started it okay so it's
in the Guardian now all right
this proof for emptiness okay this is an
approved for emptiness from the causes
side right where did it come from this
is called in later centuries later it
got a nickname called Durga Sigma D
Sigma which is what the sliver of
diamond like like and I like to tell the
story those of us who've been in the
diamond business right Tama you should
see her in the business oh my god we're
so lucky she became nun and she like
dragon you know JC Penney it was the
biggest store in the United States at
that time those guys are shaking when
she comes in the room anyway
you know one of the big diamond mines is
in Africa and so people know the diamond
is the hardest thing in the world so
people used to find a pretty big diamond
and they will come to the guy and say I
found the diamond how much money you
gonna give me the diamond buyer and the
buyer will take a hammer and go buck and
the diamond will bring and he just throw
it on the floor so it's not diamond it's
just glass okay you know go back to the
mind trying to find another one then
after the guy leaves he pick up all the
pieces because it is diamond okay
nothing can scratch a diamond in the
universe no other substance can scratch
a diamond but they're very easy to break
they're like glass if you know where the
my Mahuta yeah that's sages book if you
know the right place to hit it it will
just go top so each of those pieces of
diamond after you smash it it's pure
diamond okay no part of a diamond is
more pure than the other part it's all
100% pure carbon simple same as plants
same as human skin it's just different
atomic structure pure totally pure so it
doesn't matter you you leave it in one
piece or you're breaking into a thousand
piece each piece is pure diamond and not
different from other pieces why are we
talking about that
same with emptiness why yeah everything
in this room has its own emptiness okay
the light has its own emptiness the door
has its own emptiness you're the tip of
Dennis's nose has its own emptiness
everything has its own emptiness and
they are totally pure and they are the
same okay
they are just living in a different
place okay they attached to something
okay the cup didn't come from factory
the cup didn't come from glass the cup
didn't come from those things is the
emptiness of the cup you see the cup
didn't come from any place except from
my seats that's the emptiness of the cup
so you can say that about everything in
this room okay and it's all hundred
percent pure emptiness okay and they're
not different and they're just they're
just different things is emptiness they
belong to different things okay but it's
all it's all the same it's all like a
crystal diamond and this is one reason
why the diamond cutter Sutra is called
the diamond and why it's called diamond
cutter okay and if you want to get
geshe-la mad call it the Diamond Sutra
it's the worst translation I've ever
seen I think but there's competition so
anyway it's very interesting that Buddha
thought this this proof we shall call it
the piece of diamond this is a piece of
diamond he gave this name to this proof
it means The Guardian is number one
proof the Guardian I think it's most
important okay and we're gonna spend
some time on it okay we have to spend
some time on this proof all right it's
not as easy as it seems all right
okay and that's one of the reasons why
diamond is so important in Buddhism okay
Tantra is sometimes called diamond way
okay and when the Buddha teaches Tantra
it's as budget Dhara
holder at the diamond so these are not
just accident okay there's a big meaning
to them it's why it keeps coming up
Sanskrit root Vajra fudge cognate
vegetable okay because in ancient India
was considered to be the most powerful
thing the life force of a vegetable was
considered to be high power very high
power so they gave that name to Diamond
okay but Vajra comes from the same root
as vegetable okay because it's
considered to be a high power which is
why you should drink you're cringing
between coffee okay what are the two
problems we would see if things started
from themselves okay so now we have four
possibilities right things come from
themselves thing comes from something
else think comes from both thing comes
with no cause okay the first one what's
the problem with the first one okay then
there are two classic answers okay
famous answers in Buddhism okay there
are two very famous answers in Buddhism
why something cannot come from itself
okay number one if it came from itself
then it would already be there inside
the cause okay so a foregone tree would
be inside of a tree see okay and there
are some schools of ancient India who
believed that okay
I forget Adam I don't know if you
remember I don't remember Sankhya I
guess sank let's say inside a seed is a
full-grown tree okay
and when the seed opens you just see
what was always there you see a tree
which was always inside the seed and as
a kid you know when you're a little kid
you're like there must be the way it is
you know like forget what you learned
later when you're a kid you're like look
at the ceiling and you think mom there
must be a little tree in there you know
and then when the seed breaks open this
little tree gets out and so there must
have been a tree inside the seed from
from the beginning okay and it's a human
it's a human feeling that we have oh
that somehow the result must be inside
the cross okay
but if that were true then say to me to
make this is the first first famous
reason why not okay it's called turn man
it would be pointless for the tree to
grow it would be pointless
no no reason for the tree to grow the
good tree is already there in the city
so why go through all this trouble you
know
why put water why put fertilizer to see
this are the tree is already there so so
why were you born okay
it doesn't need to grow again it's
already complete in the scene it doesn't
need to grow again okay that's the first
reason okay
then the second famous reason okay if
you're gonna be very stubborn which is
very common for our nuns all of them all
the monks are gone okay if you're gonna
be very stubborn and you say no no it
it's the trees already in the scene but
you know the seed likes to make a tree
you know no problem so it makes another
tree what's wrong we're done you know
where your prom with that girl ah okay
then it makes a billion trees and it
never stops making trees okay if it
makes one unnecessary tree then it can
make a billion unnecessary trees got it
if it has to urge to copy itself then in
theory there's no limit it can just you
plant one seed and twenty trees will
come out okay this is called what is
that called hang on
[Music]
he has a nice
I saw something this morning oh yeah
[Music]
yeah I used a special word this morning
Satan me took me turn me took me that's
the two problems if something comes from
itself that means it's already in the
sea number one there's no reason to
retreat to grow the tree is already
there why grow another tree that's
called ten men okay there's no reason to
grow another tree if you want to grow
under the tree when you already have a
tree and if they just go anytime they
want then two men say it took me took me
means it'll just keep making trees all
day okay just extra unnecessary trees
okay if things come from themselves okay
so actually this is one of the
viewpoints in Buddhism we call
something you learned that's cool
it's not something you were born with
okay somebody told you in your religion
that inside the seed there's a tree and
when the seed opens it there's the tree
pop out you know this is just something
you learn later in your life okay we
call what II call ja ja I wish I had my
human dictionary anyway come come with
your birth you have it from birth okay
some wrong ideas you pick up some among
ideas you have when you're born okay so
it took me okay now I'm gonna go to
tomorrow's Homer because we finish
today's homework all right you know I
have a different idea I have extra time
I can go home or I can read you the
commentary okay and we can just have fun
okay you finish your homework you don't
have to write anything turn off your
mind like level seven no level eight no
fighting just turn off your mind I'm
just gonna read you from the contrary if
I had time I would rather teach this way
but I'm just trying to make things not
20 years just five years okay so I'm
gonna I read you the whole part about
the chapters okay and I'm not gonna go
through that again
so this is the part where so we're just
going to have some fun for an out an
hour Tim no break right okay you okay
for an hour okay I'm just going to go
through the contrary okay we'll just go
straight to the commentary and this is
the way I'm teaching the long room but
it's very slow so here we go
Tom chicken regular Thailand capital
tempered um how heo youngji Shenton
supersonic achievement day the reason we
are studying these examinations is not
so bad some Shepherds are means just to
have arguments with other people
okay it's not for that Chi Minh Tom
Jerry angular all of the 27 examinations
are meant to be targeted at your heart
at your own heart we want to tell them
kick we want to get the path to freedom
started in your heart then Demba we want
to make it strong and then pel WA and we
wanted to increase okay we wanted to
Chris and then he calls uma supa dupa
what's that entering the middle way who
wrote it
yeah about four four hundred fifty years
after Anna Gardner
okay and it's the most famous commentary
to Nagar Gina he wrote to actually it's
called entering the middle way okay
what's the middle way here wisdom yeah
it's a nickname for for the book okay
then he quotes chandrakirti who who
calls Chan yeah Tony Lamas Tangela turns
on the charm on Z we are not examining
all these different debates we are not
checking a thousand books because we
like to fight
we like to argue num dill journey
they need them
all those books are just to get us to
Nirvana and Buddhahood that's the only
reason okay it's not like we just enjoy
arguing okay so he uses loogie droop J
Adam yeah in Buddhism you can prove an
idea through two ways you can quote a
good author like chandrakirti or you can
prove it with logic okay
so what was his assertion we're not just
giving these 27 chapters for argument
there's a reason we're trying to improve
ourselves okay
then did he prove it then a previous
points are logic or I proved this point
through Scripture yeah he used Scripture
he is chandrakirti okay
that's a typical Buddhist thing okay
NEPA lesson 10 Gingka Tombo Tombo dead
Tama Tony :
so now I'm gonna talk more about and the
day after tomorrow but one of the great
things that Tony Lama does is he sees a
structure in this wild poem okay if you
just look at the poem if you just try to
translate the poem or you try to read
the poem it's like a psychic duck when
you call acid trip it's like some guys
this guy must be really really drunk I
must do many drunk because his mind is
just going like everywhere you know and
Tony Lama imposes a structure
Tony Lama says he's not drunk he's not
crazy he has a plan and I'll show you
the plan okay and I love these little
plans and Buddhist authors make them
very they love outlines if we had time
it would be wonderful to do an outline
if we had time it would be wonderful to
translate this book extremely valuable
okay if I had any time if I had three
weeks I could do it
anyway nipple awesome tan jianci tompa
tompa I'm gonna prove that dependence is
empty
okay I'm gonna prove Wow where'd you get
that nice
I'm going to prove that dependent
origination is empty okay
wrong change atomic number then they
told my tolling car one dog jiu-jitsu
I'm gonna show you that if you
understand emptiness you can escape the
Wheel of Life and if you don't
understand emptiness you're stuck in the
way of life I'm gonna prove it to you
that that's the difference okay does it
relate to the kitchen absolutely right
if you understand what's going on you
can break the cycle
you just run in the bathroom and yell at
yourself in the mirror and say you're
stupid okay fun funfun
you've ice bucket head I love that word
we were having dinner with Chinese
friends they brought out a real rice
bucket I said Oh fine thong everybody's
like wow that's one of my three Chinese
words then Dogma tongue and dogs'll oh
then he's gonna show how if you
understand emptiness you can't get wrong
on this you will never have stupid ideas
then there's a thousand kinds of stupid
ideas you know if your husband calls you
stupid in the kitchen then you should be
more nice you know in the evening with
your husband or you know oh there's a
roadrunner very kind of rare bird anyway
if your husband's in a bad mood you
should talk to him you know there's
things you should say there's things you
shouldn't say you know if you know blah
blah blah okay
these are called ways to not change your
husband okay
these don't change your husband why
because they don't work all the time
okay if something if you try something
and it doesn't always work stop doing it
okay
stop doing it you got the wrong one okay
like talking talking with your husband
in the evening before you go to bed
never go to bed angry then you're never
gonna sleep forget it yeah okay talk but
maybe it works maybe it doesn't work if
not a solution okay it's not it doesn't
change the causes which I in here okay
so he says once you understand emptiness
you will stop using dumb ways to change
your husband okay
there's the threat way I thought you
wanted dinner but I guess not there's
the super threat way I'm gonna have a
headache when we go to bed there's be
nice way you know I really would like a
hug I don't like to be called fantone
you know and none of them work okay
because they don't work every time okay
what's the example in DC I
don't work every time huh
let's tickets one yeah we talked about
this airline I got on song airline it's
a new airline they play songs the whole
way loud I thought well that's gonna be
nice and then the lady tried to get me
to sign an insurance waiver at the door
and I said why and she's like we almost
understand how these planes work okay
now proving that dependence has its own
emptiness has two parts we're gonna give
a proof and then in Buddhism the other
guy always gets to come back there's
always when you call rebuttal yeah he
gets in the Buddhist system you debate
the other guy you present your own
position and then you give him a chance
to criticize your position and it's very
healthy
okay then super bummer tumble on yadamma
dog number than give it up Shippo this
is the structure of wisdom okay from a
topic not from a chapter okay number one
I will teach you the two kinds of
emptiness what are they
emptiness of
people and things okay Antonis are
people and things then gay bruschetta I
will give you a big explanation to teach
the emptiness
[Music]
yeah okay we're gonna examine how
cause-and-effect works okay in order to
prove that things are empty we're gonna
examine how causes create things in
order to prove that things are empty
then we're gonna take a look at coming
and going which is Chapter two then
we're gonna take a look at coming and
going to prove that the person is empty
okay got it
chapter one helps prove that thing that
empty
Chapter two helps prove that people are
empty chapter one talks about how do
things grow from other things and
chapter 2 talks about how people can
come and go okay guy all right
[Music]
dumb bellossom objection shabbat then
Tony Lama always go through the words of
the root text and I'm not doing that
with you okay he goes word by word
through the poetry and he explains each
bird of the poetry okay
we don't have time to do that Nate don't
get long done Java means then it
connects it to other great writers other
great books okay then ten demo then the
last thing he's gonna do in the first
chapter is sent Emma Adam you gotta
guess about that he's gonna damn by the
ten of the chapter explained the ten the
name okay he's saying gonna explain the
name of the chapter why do they call it
a chapter on conditions right why did I
call it chapter that's the last thing
okay got it
I'm putting you guys to sleep I can see
that's okay okay now then it's all a big
outline okay if I ever have time to
translate you will see okay I'm not
whining I'm just complaining like a
drunken gotta results don't grow okay
first part results don't grow we're
gonna look at why results don't grow
that's the verse that we're on today
things don't come from themselves things
don't come from something else
they don't come from both they don't
come from either okay by the way we'll
keep on that tomorrow so I don't want to
tell you all the punchlines today KJ
can get on Shane gocbar and then we're
gonna look at causes and see why there's
nothing inside of them that can make
things grow okay there's nothing inside
you can say self existed you can say it
comes from its own side the husband
right in the kitchen his anger is
self-existent or it's coming from him
or it came from lack of good dinner okay
you can say all those things from its
own side but in Buddhism you can say
it's in him and it means that okay the
glass has something about it that's hard
steel has something in it which is hard
and glass especially geshe-la so cracked
has something in it which cracks okay
and you feel like it must be that
science is based on that science says
there's little pieces in there this one
has the in the third shell it has two
electrons in the first shell it has one
electron
therefore it's oxygen you know they say
it's all inside the thing and in
Buddhism that's a bad word it's like
saying four letter word but it's just
two letter word in okay don't say in
okay our angers in my husband yelling is
in my husband okay got it
not in nothing's in okay if you wanna be
like the gardener wasn't a gardener
style short you not say possessive lack
of inherent existence okay he says in
there ain't nothing in anything he said
one word no really that's his style
and people like it people when you teach
these things don't say you know this has
an inherently
in here in existence and imprimatur when
it comes it's not pedagogical what is it
epistemological lack of inherent
existence okay wouldn't ever say that
that guy would end up chapter 28 the
gardener would criticize him in chapter
28 and examination of long words all
right then we're gonna discuss results
from the viewpoint Tasha Tasha means
four choices for choices and Schanker
means do things come from something else
okay four choices means dark dedication
they can you can they can give me the
key what I mean Adam wrong the king Doc
McGhee
come from itself Shannon okay for mother
Nicola from both give me a kick it can
happen without a reason okay those are
the four choices one of them is sticky
yeah others is sticky okay others is
sticky isn't a seed other than a tree
you know isn't my mental thing other
than my husband's healing doesn't he
come from something else okay we're
gonna talk about it tomorrow okay that's
the sticky one that's the problem okay
caligo padam telethon go penny power
then he said we're gonna tomjohn
we're gonna assert we're gonna show why
we think nothing can start we'll talk
about why nothing can start okay and
then secondly we will use logic to prove
it okay we will use logic to prove it
okay
and I put my own notes in here you don't
have them you guys it's changed since
then I think I I when I have a question
I use John Brady's database I go get
when I want and I put it in the text and
then later I use it for a footnote or
something okay and I was trying to
remember what's the diamond sliver
reasoning right it came from the
gardener but what's the full proof okay
so I thought if you're not bored enough
I will give you the full proof okay
here's the proof diamond sliver proof as
it as it's taught in Buddhism okay and
this comes from
kado Damodar gay 1493 the 1568 he wrote
the textbooks for Sarah me okay 500
years ago
all right Gila Japan tour this segment
ends except Ally young let's look at the
causes of things which is called the
sliver of diamond the proof of the
sliver of diamond
okay doc Copa means first I will give
you the reason okay the the syllogism
okay syllogism means proof take what's
the four parts of a syllogism atom
number one yeah take take this clock
number two yeah it's keeping the time
number three because that's what it was
made to do it's like a car okay for four
parts to Buddhist logic take something
you want to talk about okay like tree
take a tree okay number two it doesn't
come from a scene number three why
because it grows okay something like
that so Percy's gonna give the reason
the syllogism logical statement then you
always give an example at the end it's
like the growth of fish or something
okay
let's take that so the example in the
diamond proof several diamond proof the
example is shinojima possession angry
[Music]
chinnabbai mapa things inside of you and
things outside of you okay things inside
a budget and things outside of punchy
okay don't give up on take let's take
all it means all the stuff in the world
right things that are inside Apogee and
things that are asking open I'm
searching then table I make it a they
don't grow ultimately speaking they
never grow okay ultimately speaking they
never grow okay got it
why then down by Dogma economy game they
don't grow ultimately speaking from
themselves then depression they come
again they don't go ultimately speaking
from something else
Nicolay come I can't they don't go from
ball you may let me get and they don't
go from nothing okay got it
you want to go deeper you want to get
lost completely bored out of your head
okay I think this is on a later homework
but later we'll do something else
as you know there's two schools of
there's four schools of Buddhism first
one is ancient Indian Buddhism by the
way there's four schools in Tibet that's
different right into bed there's in
historical order meaning mana the old
guys kagu the keepers of the word or
something yeah Sakia and the ones who
come from the place where the dirt is
white Sokka and then galoop some coppice
minute okay so I'm not talking about the
four schools of Tibet I'm talking about
the four schools of India what are the
four schools of India number one my body
got basically I'll be Dharma guys these
are the accountants right very dry very
dry they took they went to the Buddhist
scriptures they took out the driest part
and they made dry dry books okay so the
next school is called
Sutra sutra school because they say you
guys are just to come and you brought
all this boring stuff you know
stick with what the Buddha said it's
more interesting okay we don't like your
abhidhamma books these are just you just
took pieces out of all the sutras why
don't you just leave the Sutra alone
they're called sceptre school okay Sutra
school next cool mind only okay mine
only school basically that the things
you see around you are just part of your
mind okay basically a part of foundation
consciousness okay
and then the highest school yeah well
middle way the highest of the fourth
course is mentally okay and I'm gonna
give you a summary of what we're
studying in
right because it comes here it comes in
this class okay ready this is typical
[Music]
okay here we go
so the lower middle way school it's
called what Tantra which doesn't mean
Tantra it just means independent
independent they're called independent
group I like to call them Group two
groups inside the middle risk or okay
the middle high school high school has
two groups the lower group is called
independent okay the higher group is
called oh all fruits aren't red all
fruits are red all fruits are ready go
ahead Phil take a long thing take a long
thing yeah take a banana take bananas I
guess they're red okay that's called
pressing Vika it's a kind of logic
it's sarcastically logic the highest
middle high school name is mr. sarcastic
okay oh oh yeah okay I guess let's go
have a red banana okay I guess bananas
Iran right that's called in logic it's
called a prosecutor okay a possum geeker
also I guess your husband's gonna be
yelling in the kitchen forever you know
he started tonight and 20 years from now
he's still gonna be in the kitchen
yelling all right why are you saying
that
he's not coming from any seeds and those
things are not gonna wear out he's just
out there yelling on his own
nothing constant to you he'll yell
forever okay right and then the person
saying no no he stops yelling after two
three days usually okay so price antica
means oh I guess you can have some it's
gonna yell and tell the day he dies
right why because he's yelling from his
own side
why do you say that if he's coming from
you the good news is seeds we're out 65
per second sooner or later even if you
don't say anything the husband has to go
to bed okay so that's a present Iike
that's a passing ready oh my
husband started yelled at me why I
didn't do anything anything oh really
so he's gonna yell forever did he yell
all night is he still there in the
kitchen yelling no why do you say that
because he's not coming from you
he's not coming from your sits in your
mind which we're out every time he says
a bad word you were out like a hundred
seas okay if he says long bad words it's
better you use that more see now this is
sages tanks right Sadie he says you
should in sages text it says you should
think your husband is the Buddha why
because he's helping you use up your bad
karma he's so sweet to yell at you
anyway passing now why is the
independence code called independent
because that relates to this section
okay so there's a very famous argument
it's not in this text okay we spent a
long time on it in Sedona in the Sedona
College if you don't listen to those
classes you are crazy
in one day you get all five schools of
Buddhism you know a dream you get an
hour of deep deep and they're online
right for free that's the best way to
make people not look at them sorry so we
learned the independence called why are
they called independent because after
the gardener came a guy named Buddha
paleta a Buddha penita well I had there
someone they put up Linda okay and he
wrote an explanation of Nagarjuna okay
then came a guy named Baba me Bekka
baba me Bekka and he corrected buddha
politer he said you're wrong okay he
said you're wrong and one of the things
that Baba Rebecca said this Nagarjuna
verse is not so cool this the gardener
verse needs explanation why you could
say things don't come from themselves
that's okay and you can say things don't
come from bone and you can say things
don't come from nothing but you cannot
say things don't come from something
mouth you can't say that nobody can say
that everything comes from something
else in the gardener's text the next
verse someone's going to quote the
Buddha who
things come from other things in four
different ways
okay things come from other things in
the next verse I'm the gardener says
things do come from other things
therefore said Bobby vodka when you get
to the fourth choice things don't come
from other things you better add the
word from their own son you better add
the word from their own side okay my
opening the door doesn't make my husband
angry from its own side
okay got it you gotta add that why
because things do come from other things
okay
the gardener you should have said this
happened to me recently someone was
going to rewrite it some book anyway you
should have said things don't come from
themselves things don't come from both
things don't come from either and things
don't come self-existent lee from
something else you should have said it
that way come on because everything does
girl from causes that are others other
things got it
he said that chandrakirti comes along
and says you are fool okay
this is one I try to get his favorite
things you know you're full why you say
that you talking independence you're
talking independence
what do you mean independent you ready
you think a person who doesn't get it
when you say that things don't grow from
other things is gonna get it if you add
from their own side
you think some words have an inherent
power from their own time and you think
other words don't have an inherent power
from something else
you understand you your deepest belief
is that those words from its own side
come from their own sides they have
independent power garden I'll say it
again if I say things don't grow from
something else intelligent people will
understand
oh you mean without my theme yeah you
mean without my thing okay people who
get it will get it okay other people I
have to say look they don't grow from
something else on their own from their
own time by their very nature by in the
definition okay I have to add all those
words but listen if the guy's too stupid
to get it in the first place
he's gonna misinterpret those words too
and he's gonna think they have some
independent power and that's such a bad
habit let's call their school
independence quo they're just called
independent for three words they said
for a thousand years because they said
they wanted to add own sign from on sign
your independence and garden they made a
mistake their school believes that
things come fifty percent from the
object side and fifty percent okay
there's data out there there's colors
and shapes and and then my mind
organizes it into a into a thing they
believe done okay they think that's
that's awareness okay got it
why is that relevant here
what verts are we on things don't come
from
themselves things don't come from
something else didn't a gardener make a
mistake surely have said from their own
side from other thing by themselves from
other thing see no if you think he
should have said that then you believe
words come from themselves the power of
words comes from themselves you see then
you believe that you believe the word
from its own side has its own power
and you believe the word come from
something else doesn't have its own
power and that makes you crazy either
things have their own power everything
or everything doesn't have its own power
but don't go 5050
that's called lower-middle way okay got
it I didn't mean to go there today I
just had too much time that's the
problem of making me write a homework
because sometimes they go faster and
sometimes they go slower if I can just
wander around the book would and do
whatever I want
[Music]
okay then it gives the first Dark
Dimension a minion a man give me mean
mobile come to come a young giving them
young you mean things don't come from
themselves think they'll come from
something else things don't come from
both things don't come without any cause
everything that exists never started
okay then here's Tony Lama he made it
into a proof okay Tony Lama made it into
and there's a Sanskrit by the way we had
a really hard time putting the Sanskrit
back together many people have tried we
don't have a good manuscript but it was
quoted in other books so we put it
together you see pieces okay
and 1089 came open and conduct church
and take all the things inside a person
and outside a person toggling you don't
do don't do think kinda young so okay
I'm going deeper because we have time
and this is what I would do if we had 20
years okay but it's just cuz today that
time is slower than yesterday okay which
is impossible time consume itself
alright
the gardener says nothing at all comes
in these four ways okay he uses the word
nothing at all okay mmm come on Tina
Cucina in Sun good kumquat Chanakya
channa
nothing at all okay China katana katana
means nothing at all okay then Tony
Lamas says why did he say nothing at all
okay I didn't put this on the homework
okay because I didn't want to make you
crazy why did he say watch Anna
Kitchener in any way at all why did he
say that because it doesn't matter what
object you're talking about it doesn't
matter what time in history you're
talking about and it doesn't matter what
school of philosophy you're talking
about
place time or school question okay China
doesn't matter in any case they don't
come from them snow nobody thinks that
okay got it
kinda young kind of killing them in you
mean they dog like Kim if something were
to grow from itself doc mckenna lanka wa
din' mapa it would be meaningless for it
to start again if the tree was in the
seed already it would be meaningless for
the tree to grow from the scene okay
and Lori on Kira Cooper may be a
peculiar and it would keep having babies
for no need if it has one unnecessary
baby I'll have a hundred okay like that
okay cheatin on you go Church
let's take sprouts sprouts are very
popular in the gardener why that's what
pops up out of a scene
okay so when I say sprout don't think
sandwich sing think seed and something
coming up okay like this okay when I say
sprout think of this first you see the
head of the baby my my nephew had a baby
two days ago he wrote me email you know
we're getting in on every ten minutes
you know she's groaning she's moaning we
got here we got some here we got an inch
of head I can see an inch of head you
know like like this okay right so when I
say sprouting inch of head baby came out
fun to learn Rangi cake nipple Kayla
turn mebut are so it must be meaningless
for the sprout to come up again okay my
blankie due to no longer dummy the
chopper to Simba agent because it exists
a hundred percent complete in the sea at
the time of the sea so because it is the
same doclet k it grew from itself
therefore it's meaningless for the head
to come out the kid was already went to
college
[Laughter]
okay Mike Abner
hey and then somebody says just because
it existed completely at the time of the
seed doesn't mean it can't grow again
okay Mike up right Adam just because it
existed completely at the time of the
seed doesn't mean it can't go again
aren't you glad I didn't put all this on
your homework datachannel kill lanky or
to permeate our tupa marathon so that
must keep getting sprouts every five
minutes for the rest of eternity okay
why thank you do you know Randy Donnie
tops inkyung even though it already
exists at the time of the scene that the
sprout right young killer do you be
richer because it's not meaningless for
it to grow again
okay it's not meaningless vertical man
got it
if the kid already went to college why
have a baby again
if the baby already went to college why
have the same baby again see I mean if
the baby is full-grown
inside mom like the tree is full grown
inside the sea then there's no need to
have the baby baby already grew up
already went to school okay
already got married why why have a baby
again got it okay nobody can touch
church and now we get to the hard one
which is what yeah
things don't go from other things things
don't go from other things things don't
go from themselves is easy right except
when it's your husband yelling
that grows from itself okay watch and
take anything
Schenley num young young maintain it
doesn't go from other things ever never
my momma is to say ever never it never
ever ever never grow from other things
what's it mean never never we had in a
bomb kawatche Anika channa kabocha
nakita know what that mean that was 20
minutes ago in no way at all no place in
the world no time in history and no
school of philosophy okay not doesn't
matter why Shan like Anna couldn't
couldn't K work uhm it's something grill
from ready you okay if something could
grow from an unrelated other did I add a
word unrelated that's the trick
okay you ready it's something could grow
from an unrelated other okay then
everything would go from everything you
could plant apple seed to get banana
okay you can plant the Sandia chic WA
and you will get you'll get trucks
Toyota trucks we need right
okay all right everything will come from
everything if something can grow from
another which is unrelated okay
unrelated Oh guess not
why you add the word unrelated they
didn't say unrelated the apple tree is
related to apathy they are related it's
not just a crazy there's a relationship
apple trees come from apple seeds
it's a other thing but it's related same
family relation right
who made that okay is that inside the
seed somewhere oh yes this is genetic
there's a special small things inside
the thing you know okay not true okay
not a tree we're gonna come to it later
okay but by the time but it's a Buddhist
rule of logic that if two things are
related they have to exist at the same
time okay mas okay two kinds of
relationship possible in Buddhism
possessive or identity possession or
identity only two two kinds you know
Velma has a big bunch of money
mama Palma has a big bunch of money then
the money and Pillman are connected
they're related why belong to her now
okay she came in with the Bandito and
left without money okay then now there's
a connection possession possession okay
our lama palma is a nun this is identity
okay there's a connection okay it's
part of her identity there's two kinds
of connection possible in Buddhism but
the two things must exist at the same
time the two things must exist at the
same time okay right otherwise there's
no connection
can a tree ready can an apple tree be
connected to an apple seem impossible
why there are different time when this
okay we're gonna get to it
two days from now okay dad they cannot
be connected the seed happened before
tree happened after when that seed
approaches it destruction the tree
approaches its completion but when
they're both complete they cannot exist
at the same moment impossible okay not
possible okay okay if it if they could
not exist at the same time okay if they
could not exist at the same time and the
seed could give a tree okay with no
connection right then all things could
could bear all things all things could
come from all things right from banana
seed you will get Toyota trucks like
that okay it's not just some kind of
crazy talk okay people reading the
gardener and they say I don't want to
read this this confuse me you know I'm
already confused with my life I don't
need more computer the point is and then
we'll stop okay the point is what you
think is happening is impossible okay if
you think an apple tree can come out of
an apple seed then then in one way you
are a crazy person okay and at the whole
world okay guys if that's true then the
whole world is crazy and the guidance
say this time the gardener doesn't say
no
yeah you're right whole world is crazy
it's possible the whole world is making
a mistake okay global warming you know -
because you want to drive a car it's
possible you'll destroy this planet okay
because you cannot because you need to
drive to the store when it's a five
minute walk it's possible you will
destroy this planet for future for the
whole future it's possible the whole
world makes mistakes
it's possible big mistakes you know it's
possible so the Guardian is saying the
husband is not yelling because he
decided to yell okay it's not coming
from that where is it coming from you
yelled at the kids last scream come on
it's more logical right it's more
logical you yelled at the kids there's a
justice to the world you yelled at the
kids you said bad things you planted a
seed for bad things that's it went into
your mind and a week later the seed open
and you open the kitchen door and your
husband said bad words - it's more
logical okay
it's more logical trees seeds don't make
trees from themselves and husbands don't
decide to say bad words by themselves
it's not true it looks like that then
the whole world is living that way the
whole world is trying to send a husband
to therapy you know this will fix the
husband send them to their this will fix
the husband
yeah you have to pick the husband okay
yes okay yeah
exactly
she said if I get a partner by taking
care of an old lady isn't taking care of
the old lady something other than the
partner yeah it is in this but there's a
okay now I have to be now I have to be
lower middle way okay I'll be lower
middle way but it means that there's
something inside of the nursing home
that creates a husband you see that
there's something there which you did
not create you see you always have to
say what you did not create okay
the connection between taking care of
old ladies and me getting a partner
the connection between karma and result
is is natural it's part of nature it's
part of the universe I did not create it
I wasn't here then I wasn't around
I was busy planning to be born million
years later that wasn't created by me
okay
and that's that's the mistake if you go
to the nursing home to get a partner and
you think you are following a law of
karma which you didn't create it doesn't
work as well it doesn't work as well
okay if you think the connection between
visiting the nursing home and getting a
partner itself was not made by you then
the partner comes Lauren of that it's
very interesting it's very interesting
even the connection that we accept
between state and razón it's it's coming
from me and if you don't think that
you're thinking wrong
okay like that but that's too deep okay
all right let's did you have a question
okay you're just waving your arms sir
acne has a question
yeah
yeah okay good question I know the
question so when somebody doesn't I'll
repeat it when someone does their Gachet
degree they have to defend themselves in
both sergej and sarah me and then they
have to defend themselves in Sarah May
first to all the gadget candidates and
then to all the older gadgets and it
takes three weeks and before that you
have to defend yourself in your own
college so there are 12 colleges at
Sarah May and you have to defend
yourself in your own College and it's
tradition that the next guy to get you
questions you first so the next guy in
line to finish is get a gives the first
question so a bulk or importuning number
three is from our college because we're
the best college in the best monastery
and so he was doing his get here just
before me so I have to be his I have to
give him questions I have to be the
first question to poeple committing you
know I'm like okay then I that's Iraq
knees the question you know I said our
Buddhists surrounded is the definition
of buna part of the definition if they
are surrounded by tenth level body
stammers then he said yes then I say do
those people see themselves are they
somewhere else or some other Buddha
paradise or could it be right here he
says could be right here because
everything's empty then I said well well
so is it possible that I reach
Buddhahood and I see everybody around me
as tenth level Bodhisattva because my
mind is pure right
yes and is it possible they don't see
themselves as tension among Buddhists
and I said yeah of course
so I said well then they must be
suffering right they're not temple
everybody stop they must be suffering
right so just buna see everything yes so
that's bonus see that they don't see
themselves as buna yes
so does Buddha see them suffering yes if
a goodness is suffering then the Buddha
has seen in their mind for suffering
right like time you know then the debate
master said oh then he drops his shop
and it means you stop it's like we can't
embarrass this Rimba change you know
let's leave it you know and I'm like
come on this is something I really want
to know so that the Lama who became the
head of give me a tender college we went
out on the porch and we started arguing
for three hours or this question okay
and it means I don't know
[Laughter]
okay let's stop there I see you tomorrow
ginger team
[Music]
some girl
scene
- bye
[Music]
she
show me